Guide to the Alvin P. Shapiro Papers, 1942-1998 UA.90.F64
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Published Abstracts and Discussions, 1950-1997; III.
  - Factors Predicting the Development of Renal Involvement in Progressive Systemic Sclerosis (PSS), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Response of Patients with Progressive Systemic Sclerosis to Antihypertensive Therapy, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Response of CBF to Treatment in Elderly Patients with SH, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Book Review, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Stress and Hypertension: a Clinical Challenge, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Nonpharmacologic Intervention: Discussion, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Letter to the Editor, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Book Review, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Letter to the Editor, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Behavioural techniques not a substitute for the physician and his drugs, says Shapiro, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - BP Variability: No Change with Age, Type, Severity or Treatment of Hypertension, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Book Review, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - New Hypertension Following Cardiac Transplantation, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Book Review, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Book Review, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Letter to the Editor, 1983-1984 (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Essential Hypertension - Pathogenetic Suggestions from Repeated Hemodynamic Investigations in Young Men With Blood Pressure Elevation, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - In Memoriam: Gerald P. Rodnan, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - Letter to the Editor, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - Relaxation, Pharmacotherapy and Their Interaction in the Treatment of Mild Hypertension, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Biobehavioral Approaches to Hypertension: Relaxation Therapy, Pharmacotherapy, and Their Interaction, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Reversing the Effects of Elevated Blood Pressure on the Central Nervous System by Antihypertensive Treatment, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - The Response of Cyclosporine Toxicity to Azathioprine and Reduced Cyclosporine Dose, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - Similarities and Differences in Test-Taking Behaviors by Hypertensive and Normotensive Subjects, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Minoxidil in Once-a-Day Triple Therapy for Mild, Moderate and Severe Hypertension, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Nocturnal Blood Pressure Decrease, Cardiac Transplantation and Diabetes with Autonomic Neuropathy, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - The Contrasting Effects of Cyclosporin-A and Azathioprine on Arterial Blood Pressure and Renal Function Following Cardiac Transplantation, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 89)
  - Blood Pressure Monitoring and Pill Placebo: Experiences with Two Different Methods of Inducing Nonspecific Treatments Effects for Mild Hypertensives, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 90)
  - Letter to the Editor, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 91)
  - Hypertension, Creatine, and Plasma Renin Activity in Heart Transplant Recipients, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 92)
  - Renal Artery Stenosis in Blacks, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 93)
  - Renal Artery Stenosis in Blacks [RESTRICTED], 1986 (Box 2, Folder 94)
  - Cholesterol Emboli: Relation to Cardiac Catheterization and a Review of Its Clinical Presentations, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 95)
  - Book Review, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 96)
  - Can Self-Help Methods Cure Disease? Treating Illness with Behavioral Medicine, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 97)
  - Relation of Ambulatory Blood Pressure and Treatment Outcomes, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 98)
  - Ambulatory Blood Pressure: Value in Patient Care, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 99)
  - AIDS Victims Helped, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 100)
  - Point/Counterpoint: Are diuretics appropriate as first-line therapy for hypertensives with a family history of diabetes?, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Behavioral Therapies for Hypertension: Current Status, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Neuropsychological Performance of Hypertensive and Normotensive Males, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Book Review, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Behavioral Therapies for Hypertension: Current Status, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Age and Hypertension Independently Slow Cognitive Transformation, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Temperature Biofeedback-assisted Relaxation: A Treatment for White Coat Hypertension?, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Letter to the Editor, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 108)
  - Stress Management with Hypertension: Regression to the Mean and Setting Specific Effects, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 109)
  - Neurobehavioral Effects of Antihypertensive Medications in Hypertensive Men, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 110)
  - Letter to the Editor, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 111)
  - Antihypertensive Drugs Show Age-Dependent Effects on Short Term Vigilance, But Not Working Memory, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 112)
  - Neuropsychological Performance of Untreated, Male Hypertensives: Effects of Age, Education, and Alcohol Consumption, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 113)
  - Letter to the Editor, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 114)
  - Neuropsychological Sequelae of Antihypertensive Medications, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 115)
  - Neuropsychological Performance Effects of Antihypertensive Medications, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 116)
  - Clinical Trials in the 90s and Beyond, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 117)
  - A "Biased View": Current Drugs in the Treatment of Mild Hypertension, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 118)
  - Ruminations from Two Curmudgeons, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 119)
  - Book Review, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 120)
- Published Manuscripts, 1961-1998; 1971-1998; IV.
  This series contains published manuscripts and relating draft materials, research data sheets, graphs, notes, correspondence, publication submission forms, peer-review documents, and publication proof materials from the latter majority of Shapiro's professional career. During this time, Shapiro's research continued to examine the relationship between stress and hypertension, hypertension and renal function related to systemic scleroderma, as well as pharmacologic and behavioral treatments to control hypertension. Throughout this period, Shapiro was also becoming more involved with the administration of the University of Pittsburgh's medical school, Presbyterian University Hospital, and Shadyside Hospital, where he served, at various times, as dean for academic affairs, chairman of the credentials committee, and director of the internal medicine training program respectively. His service in these capacities is reflected in several publications that critique medical training at universities and hospitals. Documents are arranged chronologically.
  Some files in this section include the personal and medical information of human study subjects and access is governed by certain restrictions. In Box 2, Folders 125 and 127 are restricted. In Box 3, Folders 5, 7, 20, and 26 are restricted. In Box 4, Folders 21 and 23 are restricted. In Box 5, Folders 4 and 12 are restricted. In Box 6, Folders 16, 22, and 28 are restricted.
  - Effect of Thiazides on Carbohydrate Metabolism in Patients with Hypertension, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 121)
  - Patterns of Pressor Response to Noxious Stimuli in Normal, Hypertensive, and Diabetic Subjects, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 122)
  - Differences in Perception Between Hypertensive and Normotensive Populations, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 123)
  - Development of Bacteriuria in a Hypertensive Population: A 7-year Follow-up Study, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 124)
  - Development of Bacteriuria in a Hypertensive Population: A 7-year Follow-up Study [RESTRICTED], 1971 (Box 2, Folder 125)
  - Technique of Controlled Drug Assay in Hypertension. V. Comparison of Hydrochlorothiazide with a New Quinethazone Diuretic, Metolazone, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 126)
  - Technique of Controlled Drug Assay in Hypertension. V. Comparison of Hydrochlorothiazide with a New Quinethazone Diuretic, Metolazone, [Raw Data], [RESTRICTED], 1971 (Box 2, Folder 127)
  - Studies of Antibiotic Persistence in the Therapy of Experimental Pyelonephritis: Insoluble Tetracyclines in Normal and Pyelonephritic Rats, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 128)
  - The Role of Psychosocial Factors in the Development of Arteriosclerosis in CBA Mice, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 129)
  - Comparison of Ethacrynic Acid and Hydrochlorothiazide in Hypertension, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 130)
  - Malignant Hypertension Following Renal Artery Branch Obstruction, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Behavioral Approach to the Study of Cardiovascular Disease in Man, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Essential Hypertension - Why Idiopathic?, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Effects of Practolol on Pressor Responses to Noxious Stimuli in Hypertensive Patients, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Effects of Practolol on Pressor Responses to Noxious Stimuli in Hypertensive Patients [RESTRICTED], 1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Comparison of Pressor and Adrenergic Responses Derived from Direct and Indirect Methods of Cardiovascular Testing, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Comparison of Pressor and Adrenergic Responses Derived from Direct and Indirect Methods of Cardiovascular Testing [RESTRICTED], 1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Long-term Study of Relationships Between Blood Pressure, Age, and Body Weight in Steel Mill Workers, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Hypertension: Where do we go from here?, [1973] (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Mechanisms of Blood Pressure Elevation in Pyelonephritic Rats After Sodium Loading, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Perspectives on the Renin-Angiotensin-Aldosterone System in Hypertension, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - The Use of Behavioral Objectives in the Development and Evaluation of a Third-year Surgical Clerkship, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Effect of Intermittent Electric Shock on Plasma Renin Activity in Rats, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Blood Pressure and Heart-Rate Response to Verbal Instruction and Relaxation in Hypertension, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - The Impact of Curricular Change on Performance on National Board Examinations, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - In Memoriam: I. Arthur Mirsky, M.D., 1975 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Relationships of the Renin-Angiotensin-Aldosterone System and Sodium Balance to Blood Pressure Regulation in Chronic Renal Failure of Polycystic Kidney Disease, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Blood Pressure Regulation in Chronic Renal Failure of Polycystic Kidney Disease, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Relationships of Perception, Cognition, Suggestion and Operant Conditioning in Essential Hypertension, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Relationships of Perception, Cognition, Suggestion and Operant Conditioning in Essential Hypertension [RESTRICTED], 1975 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Presidential Address - 1975: Before the Colors Fade (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Blood Pressure Regulation During Chronic Renal Failure Due to Polycystic Renal Disease, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Treatment of Severe Hypertension with Minoxidil, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Guest Editorial: The leaning ivied tower, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Renal Arterial Stenosis and Hypertension II. Current Criteria for Surgery, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Renal Arterial Stenosis and Hypertension II. Current Criteria for Surgery [RESTRICTED], 1976 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Behavioral Methods in the Treatment of Hypertension: A Review of Their Clinical Status, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Hypertensive Encephalopathy with Cortical Blindness, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Effects of Hemodialysis and Saline Loading on Body Fluid Compartments, Plasma Renin Activity and Blood Pressure in Patients on Chronic Hemodialysis, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Hypertension in Radiation Nephritis, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Behavioral Approaches to the Treatment of Hypertension, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Cardiovascular Diseases: Psychosomatic Aspects, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Hypertension - Current Management: Parts I and II, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Non-Pharmacologic Treatment of Hypertension, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - The Utility Function of Antihypertensive Therapy: Discussion, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Treatment of Severe Hypertension, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Behavioral and Environmental Aspects of Hypertension, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Non-A, Non-B Types: A Parable for Behaviorists, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Pathophysiology of Stress-Induced Hypertension, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Behavioral Medicine Approaches to Hypertension: An Integrative Analysis of Theory and Research, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Hypertension: Where we are now, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Proteinuria and Nephrotic Syndrome Induced by Renin in Patients With Renal Artery Stenosis, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Behavior Modification: Can it Control Hypertension, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Universities, Medical Schools, and Hospitals - Can They Coexist?, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Complications of Antihypertensive Therapy, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Attitudes of Physicians Concerning Controversial Issues in Hypertension, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Increased Amphetamine Stereotypy and Longer Haloperidol Catalepsy in Spontaneously Hypertensive Rats, Undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Response of Patients with Renal Involvement by Progressive Systemic Sclerosis to Antihypertensive Therapy, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Pathophysiological Aspects of Hypertension, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Stress and Hypertension, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Behavioral Consequences of Mild Hypertension, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Cerebral Blood Flow Changes with Diuretic Therapy in Elderly Subjects with Systolic Hypertension, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Physiological, Psychological, and Social Determinants in Hypertension, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - The Non-Pharmacologic Treatment of Hypertension, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
  - Psychological and Social Factors in Hypertension, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Pseudopseudohypoparathyroidism and Pheochromocytoma: Association or Coincidence?, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Hypertension and Renal Failure (Scleroderma Renal Crisis) in Progressive Systemic Sclerosis, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 18-20)
  - Hypertension and Renal Failure (Scleroderma Renal Crisis) in Progressive Systemic Sclerosis [RESTRICTED], 1983 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - New Onset of Hypertension Following Cardiac Transplantation: A Preliminary Report and Analysis, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - New Onset of Hypertension Following Cardiac Transplantation: A Preliminary Report and Analysis [RESTRICTED], 1983 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Management of the Elderly Patient with Renovascular Hypertension, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Ambulatory Blood Pressure Monitoring: Methods to Assess Severity of Hypertension, Variability and Sleep Changes, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Factors Predicting the Development of Renal Involvement in Progressive Systemic Sclerosis, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Effect of Antihypertensive Treatment on the Behavioral Consequences of Elevated Blood Pressure, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - The Relaxation Word of the Day: A Simple Technique to Measure Adherence to Relaxation, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - 15-Hydroxyprostaglandin Dehydrogenase and Hexokinase in Spontaneously Hypertensive Rat Kidney, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Behavioral Consequences of Hypertension, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Temporal Relationships of Treatment with Angiotensin Converting Enzyme Inhibitors on the Hypertension and Cardiac Hypertrophy in Spontaneously Hypertensive Rats, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Pathogenesis and Pharmacologic Management of Pseudo-Obstruction of the Bowel in Pheochromocytoma, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Hypertension in the Elderly Part VIII: Renal Effects of Antihypertensive Drugs in the Elderly, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Loss of Nocturnal Decline in Blood Pressure Developing After Cardiac Transplantation, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Loss of Nocturnal Decline in Blood Pressure Developing After Cardiac Transplantation [RESTRICTED], 1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Methodological Considerations in Ambulatory Blood Pressure Monitoring, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Pharmacologic Agents as Modulators of Stress, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Contrasting Effects of Cyclosporin-A and Azathioprine on Arterial Blood Pressure and Renal Function Following Cardiac Transplant, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Once-a-Day Triple Therapy with Low-Dose Minoxidil for Moderate Hypertension, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Test-Taking Behaviors by Hypertensive and Normotensive Individuals, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Cardiac Transplantation 1985: Hope -- Promise -- Reality, 1985-1986 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Relaxation Therapy for Hypertension: Comparison of Effects with Concomitant Placebo, Diuretic, and B-Blocker, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Relaxation Therapy for Hypertension: Comparison of Effects with Concomitant Placebo, Diuretic, and B-Blocker [RESTRICTED], 1986 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Drug Therapy in Hypertension, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Behavioral Consequences of Hypertension and Their Relationship to Personality, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Nonpharmacologic Therapy of Hypertension in Blacks, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - The Behavioral Treatment of Hypertension: Long-Term Effects, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Behavioral Consequences of Hypertension and Their Relationship to Personality of Patients with this Disorder, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Hypertension in Women: Differences and Implications, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Inhibitors of Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme in the Management of Hypertension, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Inhibitors of Angiotensin Converting Enzyme in the Management of Hypertension, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Definition and Classification of Hypertension, Undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Renal Involvement in Systemic Sclerosis, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Patient Characteristics and Their Influence on Therapy and Its Outcome in Hypertension of the Elderly, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Teaching Behavioral Concepts in Cardiovascular Disease with Remarks and Challenges to Medical Education, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - The Statistical Analysis of Treatment Effects in 24-Hour Ambulatory Blood Pressure Recordings, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Cholesterol Emboli After Cardiac Catheterization: Eight Cases and a Review of the Literature, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Psychological Factors in Hypertension: An Overview, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Drug-Induced Illnesses as a Cause for Admission to a Community Hospital, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Hypertension Following Orthotopic Cardiac Transplantation, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Behavioral Consequences of Hypertension: Effects of Age and Type of Antihypertensive Agent, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Absence of Behavioral Differences in Young Normotensive Adults as a Function of Parental History of Hypertension, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Outcome of Renal Crisis in Systemic Sclerosis: Relation to Availability of Angiotensin Converting Enzyme (ACE) Inhibitors, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Hypertension, Creatine, and Plasma Renin Activity in Heart Transplant Recipients, 1990 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Relaxation Therapy for Hypertension: Design Effects and Treatment Effects, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Who Really Determines Your Patients' Prescriptions, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Behavioral Aspects of Cardiovascular Disease, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Behavioral Sequelae of Antihypertensive Therapy: A Review, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - The Confusing Syndromes of Cardiovascular Autonomic Imbalance: Cardiovascular Dysautonomias, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Neurobehavioral Effects of Antihypertensive Medications, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Renal Involvement in Systemic Sclerosis, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Relaxation Therapy for Hypertension: Setting-Specific Effects, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Clinical Use of Ambulatory Blood Pressure Recording: Value in Patient Care, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Clinical Use of Ambulatory Blood Pressure Recording: Value in Patient Care [RESTRICTED], 1992 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Illness and Death in American Presidents, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Renal Involvement in Systemic Sclerosis, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Editorials for the Bulletin of the Allegheny County Medical Society, 1993-1996 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Is the Effect of Stress Management on Blood Pressure Just Regression to the Mean?, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - A Prospective Randomized Controlled Trial to Evaluate the Effect of Prophylactic Nifedipine on Renal Function in Patients Administered Contrast Media, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - A Prospective Randomized Controlled Trial to Evaluate the Effect of Prophylactic Nifedipine on Renal Function in Patients Administered Contrast Media [RESTRICTED], 1994 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Cardiac Transplantation: A Quarter Century of Progress, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Reversible Nephrotic Syndrome Due to High Renin State in Renovascular Hypertension, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Blood Pressure and Behavioral Effects of Antihypertensive Medications: A Preliminary Report, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Clinical Use of Ambulatory Blood Pressure Monitoring, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 26-27)
  - Clinical Use of Ambulatory Blood Pressure Monitoring [RESTRICTED], 1995 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Systolic Hypertension in Critical Aortic Stenosis and the Effect of Valve Replacement, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Hypertension and Neuropsychological Performance in Men: Interactive Effects of Age, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Management of Hypertension with Particular Attention to the Renin-Angiotensin System, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Renal Involvement in Systemic Sclerosis, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Cerebral Blood Flow in Hypertensive Patients: An Initial Report of Reduced and Compensatory Blood Flow Responses During Performance of Two Cognitive Tasks, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Psychological Factors in Hypertension: An Overview, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Book Drafts and Materials, 1991-1996; V.
  This series includes draft materials from the book, Perspectives in Behavioral Medicine: Behavioral Aspects of Cardiovascular Disease, co-edited by Shapiro and Andrew Baum, and draft materials from Shapiro's monograph, Hypertension and Stress: A Unified Concept. Both books, published in the 1990s, represent the culmination of hypertension research from Shapiro's professional career. Documents are arranged chronologically.
  - Behavioral Aspects of Cardiovascular Disease, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Hypertension and Stress: A Unified Concept, 1992-1996 (Box 7, Folder 2-6)
- Personal Papers, 1942-1998; VI.
  This series is divided into two subseries: Military Records and Correspondence. Scope and Content Notes are included with each subseries.
  - Military Records, 1942-1953; 1. (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
    This subseries includes records, certificates, and orders from Shapiro's time in the United States Army. Shapiro was drafted into the U.S. Army Enlisted Reserve Corps in May 1943 while he was still a medical student. He completed medical school in September 1944, entered a medical internship until July 1945, and finished his residency in April 1946. He was then sent to Fort Sam Houston, TX for military medical training, and afterward served in the hospital at the Army Air Base in Adak, Alaska until October 1947. In 1950, Shapiro received notification that he was to be inducted into Selective Services because his previous service had been terminated earlier than usual. It was ultimately determined that he was not required to serve additional time in the military - this series includes correspondence regarding this matter. These documents are arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1953-1981; 1974-1979; 2. (Box 7, Folder 9-10)